<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-09T22:03:19-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mike’s Musings</title><subtitle>Personal website for Mike Sturm, a firmware engineer from Edmond, Oklahoma.</subtitle><author><name>Mike Sturm</name></author><entry><title type="html">A Tribute to My Dad</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/tribute-to-dad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tribute to My Dad" /><published>2020-03-02T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-03-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/tribute-to-dad</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/tribute-to-dad/">&lt;p&gt;My Dad, Gene Paul Sturm, Jr., of Bartlesville, OK passed away on March 2, 2020 after years of
struggle against Alzheimer’s Disease. Below is a tribute to my father, friend, and mentor.
I will never forget him and his tremendous, positive impact on my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the book of Matthew, Jesus teaches&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Love the Lord your God with all your heart and with all your soul and with all your mind.
This is the first and greatest commandment. And the second is like it: Love your neighbor as
yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Matthew 22:37-39 (NRSV)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that my dad understood and believed these words by the way he lived his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dad demonstrated his &lt;strong&gt;love for God&lt;/strong&gt; not only through sharing his faith and values within our
family, but by recognizing the image of God in everyone and by marveling at the beauty of the
universe He created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dad demonstrated his &lt;strong&gt;love for his neighbors&lt;/strong&gt; by selflessly serving his community, his friends,
and especially his family.  He practiced sacrificial love, putting his own needs below the needs
of those he loved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/genesturm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gene Paul Sturm, Jr.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; recipient of Dad’s love, and his values forever shaped me into the husband and
the father I am today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who always believed the best in people instead of the worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who valued honesty and justice for those in society who were overlooked
and marginalized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who was brilliant but never made you feel any less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who taught that loving God and loving science are not mutually exclusive
but the truest expressions of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who believed in me as I pursued my educational and career dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who showed me how to treat family and friends with unrelenting love and
respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who loved my wife like his own daughter and who had overflowing love and
pride for his grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am mostly &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who taught me to &lt;strong&gt;love God and love others&lt;/strong&gt; - the values I
need to live my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will miss Dad until I see him in Heaven, but I know that I carry his values with me every day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mike Sturm</name></author><category term="Family" /><category term="Dad" /><category term="God" /><category term="Christianity" /><summary type="html">My Dad, Gene Paul Sturm, Jr., of Bartlesville, OK passed away on March 2, 2020 after years of struggle against Alzheimer’s Disease. Below is a tribute to my father, friend, and mentor. I will never forget him and his tremendous, positive impact on my life.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Christmas Presence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/christmas-presense/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christmas Presence" /><published>2010-12-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2010-12-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/christmas-presense</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/christmas-presense/">&lt;p&gt;One of my fondest childhood memories of Christmas has to be &lt;em&gt;The Cheetah&lt;/em&gt;.  No, I am not talking
about the fastest of all land mammals.  For those of you who were not a young boy in the early
1970’s, the cheetah was the pinnacle of ride-on toys.  This was no wimpy “Big Wheel” - its name
promised a more exhilarating experience.  I imagined that with this vehicle, I could zoom down
my neighborhood sidewalks in Bartlesville, Oklahoma as fast as the animal for which it was named.
In my mind it epitomized the ultimate Christmas gift, and of course I let everyone know it was
at the top of my wish list.  The memory of receiving this gift and racing down the street is
clearly imprinted in my memory to this day.  Few other gifts made this kind of impression on me
growing up.  Of course there were a few exceptions, but for the most part I do not remember
many of the other Christmas presents from my childhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/cheetah.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Cheetah&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;traditions&quot;&gt;Traditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say my memories of Christmas are fuzzy.  Christmas was always a time of great
anticipation at our house, and not only for the toys that were sure to be opened on the night
of Christmas Eve.  For us the season started around Thanksgiving with our annual trek up into
the attic to retrieve the boxes of decorations.  Climbing into the dusty attic seemed like a
rite of passage to me, and if you saw my wide eyes you would think I was on a safari or other
adventure (perhaps to a galaxy far, far away).  Usually this ritual found my dad crawling back
to the far corners of the space and pushing box after box to me.  I would either take the boxes
down the stairs or hand them to my brother below.  We felt so proud to help with the boxes.
Because of our family tendency for horrible allergies, our Christmas tree came in a box with
each branch color-coded to indicate the placement on the green metal “trunk”.  Even though
artificial trees can never fully substitute for the beauty of a real one, our tree always
seemed beautiful to us despite being loaded down with so many ornaments, lights, garland,
and icicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Christmas Eve, the celebration kicked into high gear.  I always looked forward to the special
candlelight church service, not so much for the many Christmas carols we sang but for the
opportunity to hold a lighted candle in church!  Cool!  At the front of the sanctuary advent
candles were lighted, and the flame was transferred one by one to individual handheld candles
throughout the room.  My family usually sat in a pew towards the back of the auditorium, so to me
it always seemed to take forever to get the flame to our candles.  I swear that on some nights
“Silent Night” was almost over by the time the flame arrived.  As I remember, the experience of
holding the candle and raising it up and down at key moments of the song was well worth the wait.
It is a miracle that our church didn’t burn to the ground given the number of children wielding
fire!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/fcc-sanctuary.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First Christian Church, Bartlesville, OK&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course after “Silent Night” concluded, all that was on my mind was getting back home to the
Christmas presents.  No chatting with other families - let’s go home!  Presents awaited us at the
house, not to be outdone by dozens of snacks prepared by my mom.  There were pretzels covered in
chocolate, peanut butter balls dipped in chocolate, chocolate pie, and did I mention chocolate?
A deli tray with cuts of meat and cheese awaited those who did not crave sweets.  Usually my
brother and I were able to convince the family that we should open the presents before (or at
least during) snacking.  The eager boys would always hand out the presents, and then all of us
would go around the room opening our gifts in order of youngest to oldest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the hoopla surrounding Christmas Eve subsided, Christmas morning was somewhat anticlimactic.
It was time for one “Santa” gift plus some token gifts in the stockings.  At the risk of sounding
like an old-timer, the only apple products in our stockings were the edible kind…. and we
LOVED IT!  (Okay, this comment was for the benefit of my children who are usually treated to iPods,
DVDs, and CDs.)  I also remember sometimes getting to meet Santa at our house.  One of my family
members would dress the part and deliver mesh “stockings” filled with fruit and trinkets.  I don’t
remember if we knew it was him in the Santa suit or not - I guess we were too mesmerized by the
fruit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/santa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Santa Claus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;christmas-presence&quot;&gt;Christmas Presence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now as a husband and father of three, I look back at my childhood from a different perspective.
Just as countless other parents have discovered through the centuries, I appreciate Christmas as a
time for families to connect and reconnect.  As the charity Advent Conspiracy so cleverly reminds
us, Christmas is about presence not presents.  Christmas presence is being there (and not
twittering on your iPhone) with your spouse and children.  Christmas presence is creating family
memories and meaningful traditions.  Christmas presence is sharing God’s love with others through
sacrificial generosity.  Most of all, Christmas presence is reflecting on how much we are loved by God.
God gave us His presence in the form of a baby born in Bethlehem about 2000 years ago.  With the birth
of Jesus, God told the world that he wanted an intimate relationship with each one of us.  He wanted
to be present in our lives just like a good father is for his children.  God modeled perfect love for
us not from afar, but with us, in person on this planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so thankful for my parents, brother, grandparents, aunts, uncles and cousins for sharing
Christmas experiences and loving me in my childhood.  I am so thankful to have a wonderful wife and
children (and extended family) with which to create new Christmas memories.  Most of all, I am
thankful to Jesus for sharing His Christmas presence with the world.  I guess for me Christmas
presence is all about thanksgiving.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mike Sturm</name></author><category term="Christmas" /><category term="God" /><category term="Christianity" /><summary type="html">One of my fondest childhood memories of Christmas has to be The Cheetah. No, I am not talking about the fastest of all land mammals. For those of you who were not a young boy in the early 1970’s, the cheetah was the pinnacle of ride-on toys. This was no wimpy “Big Wheel” - its name promised a more exhilarating experience. I imagined that with this vehicle, I could zoom down my neighborhood sidewalks in Bartlesville, Oklahoma as fast as the animal for which it was named. In my mind it epitomized the ultimate Christmas gift, and of course I let everyone know it was at the top of my wish list. The memory of receiving this gift and racing down the street is clearly imprinted in my memory to this day. Few other gifts made this kind of impression on me growing up. Of course there were a few exceptions, but for the most part I do not remember many of the other Christmas presents from my childhood.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Parable of the Comet</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/parable-of-the-comet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parable of the Comet" /><published>2010-11-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-11-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/parable-of-the-comet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/parable-of-the-comet/">&lt;p&gt;I have a confession - I am an astronomy geek.  That may not be much of a surprise to those of you
who have seen my 8 inch telescope or watched my excitement looking to the skies from a dark,
country location away from the bright lights of the city.  Astronomy captured my imagination early
in my life and has captivated me ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;for-the-love-of-comets&quot;&gt;For the love of comets…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of my astronomical affection is focused on the lonely comet.  Astronomers theorize that many
of these small bodies of dust and ice orbit our sun at a very great distance in a large spherical
Oort cloud.  Small tugs of gravity from planets or other stars may cause one of the cold, dark
comets to plunge towards the sun into the inner solar system where it may put on a spectacular
show.  Comet tails of gas, dust, ice are blown away from the comet by the solar wind and
illuminated by reflected sunlight.  Given a favorable combination of proximity to Earth and angle
of illumination by the Sun, a comet’s tail may appear to stretch across a considerable portion
of the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the most famous of all comets is Halley’s Comet.  The orbit of Halley’s comet causes it
to visit the inner solar system about once every 75 years, and for the 1986 visit I was eager to
catch a glimpse of my first comet.  In spite of cautions from astronomers that this particular
appearance of the noteworthy visitor would be disappointing due to the Earth’s position relative
to its approach, my family and I set off one cold spring morning to view the comet before sunrise.
With star maps in hand we were barely able to find the fuzzball near the southern horizon.
Spectacular comets would have to wait for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, that day came ten years after the dismal performance of Halley.  In March 1996, Comet
Hyakutake passed very close to the Earth, and because of its close proximity and long gas tail,
this comet was simply incredible to behold from the pitch black sky I found near Stillwater,
Oklahoma.  I was amazed by the huge tail that seemed to span about half of the sky like a giant
search light.  Armed with a 35 mm camera, tripod, and fast film, I captured some of my first
photographs of a comet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/hyakutake5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Comet Hyakutake, near Stillwater, OK 1996&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a year later, another incredible comet graced the Oklahoma skies.  Comet Hale-Bopp, predicted
to be bright and beautiful, did not disappoint those who saw it over several months of naked-eye
visibility.  I captured a photograph if it hanging above the silos at my wife’s family farm near
Cushing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Hale-Bopp-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Comet Hale-Bopp, near Cushing, OK 1997&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On November 4, 2010 the NASA EPOXI spacecraft will fly by Comet Hartley 2, and of course I will
be following the encounter on the NASA website!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;parable-of-the-comet&quot;&gt;Parable of the Comet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder what it must have been like for our ancestors to see comets hanging in the sky.  For
those without electric lights to artificially brighten the sky at night, comets would have been
more visible, impressive, and perhaps even ominous.  History records that ancient peoples often
feared comets as foreboding signs of horrible events to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Bible does not record any stories that Jesus told about comets, I imagine that he
would have pointed to comets not as signs of evil but rather demonstrations of God’s love for us
and reminders of our relationship with the Son.  For you see, we are all like comets created from
dust left over from an ancient supernova.  When we are far from the Son, our hearts are frozen and
we are alone in darkness.  Yet even in our darkest moments, the Son draws us to Him.  As we humbly
approach the Son, our hearts melt and we lose ourselves in the warmth of His love.  The Holy
Spirit is a wind from the Son that strips away our hurts, loneliness, and selfishness and reveals
the Son.  The nearer we get to the Son, the more we reflect His light to others who are watching
in the darkness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love comets because they draw me to the Son.  When I look up at the amazing universe that God
has created, I want to live my life reflecting the Son’s light - not to draw attention to myself,
but to lead those in the darkness to Him.  After all, God loved each of us so much that He gave
us the Son, and whoever approaches the Son will not be filled with coldness, darkness, and death
but with warmth, light, and life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mike Sturm</name></author><category term="Astronomy" /><category term="Comet" /><category term="God" /><category term="Christianity" /><summary type="html">I have a confession - I am an astronomy geek. That may not be much of a surprise to those of you who have seen my 8 inch telescope or watched my excitement looking to the skies from a dark, country location away from the bright lights of the city. Astronomy captured my imagination early in my life and has captivated me ever since.</summary></entry></feed>