<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-14T19:56:07-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mike’s Musings</title><subtitle>Personal website for Mike Sturm, a firmware engineer from Edmond, Oklahoma.</subtitle><author><name>Mike Sturm</name></author><entry><title type="html">Remembering summers with Dad</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/fathers-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Remembering summers with Dad" /><published>2020-06-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-06-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/fathers-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/fathers-day/">&lt;p&gt;For my brother Mark and me, this is our first Father’s Day without Dad, who passed away in March.
For many years, Alzheimer’s Disease slowly robbed our family of Dad’s full presence.
At first, it slightly diminished his exceptional intellect, giving the rest of us a fighting chance
to win an occasional round of Liverpool Rummy. As it progressed, this horrible illness stole his
words and deprived him of the ability to recount humorous stories from his childhood and verbal
expressions of his love for us. Ultimately it claimed his life, long before it should have ended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, Alzheimer’s Disease cannot and will not steal our memories of a man who humbly and
honorably taught two boys how to be an excellent father through his consistent example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope each of you enjoys Father’s Day as much as I enjoy &lt;em&gt;remembering summers with Dad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/fathersday.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Happy Father's Day&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Happy Father’s Day&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;outdoor-adventures&quot;&gt;Outdoor adventures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dad loved spending time outside and shared his enthusiasm with us each summer, guiding
us as we explored various outdoor hobbies and sports. A gifted athlete himself, Dad was skilled in
baseball, basketball, golf, and many other sports. I appreciate how he encouraged us but never
forced us to play a particular sport. I have seen other fathers push their children to follow
in their footsteps to recapture their youth. Dad used a different approach. He devoted
himself to helping us experience many new activities, such as showing us how to catch a fish
or how to hit a baseball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/fishing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fishing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Dad is holding quite possibly the only fish I ever caught…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dad knew the best balance of encouragement and instruction to help us find hobbies and paths to success. I remember his kindness one time after I made a crucial mistake while running
the bases after a hit. I ran past second base to third and then found myself standing by my fellow
teammate at third base! Oops, where did he come from? I was easily tagged out as I ran back to
second. Upon my return to the dugout, I could hear other fathers grumbling about my costly gaffe.
Dad lovingly explained how to avoid that mistake in the future and, most importantly, assured me
that I was loved even in times of failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/baseball.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Baseball&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Swing batter…batter…miss!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each year, Dad and Granddad planted a large vegetable garden with rows of asparagus, okra,
pumpkins, watermelon, cantaloupe, green beans, and sometimes corn. When Mark and I were old enough
to help with manual labor, we joined them in the tasks of watering and pulling weeds in the garden
during the long, hot days of summer. At the time, both of us complained about this hard work, but
Dad knew that it would teach us deeper lessons about life itself - the value of working hard so
you can enjoy a harvest. I look back at this time fondly, and I credit those lessons learned
as the foundations of my work ethic today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/garden.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gardening&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;That glazed look after realizing you are going to pick a ton of vegetables…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our favorite activities in the summer was playing golf at Adams Municipal Golf Course
in Bartlesville. Granddad and Dad had many years of experience playing golf, and it showed.
Not only had they mastered the game, but they understood the subtle points of golf etiquette
which were often lost on Mark and me. They would kindly show us how to mark our ball position on
the green, how to repair divots, how to avoid walking on the green between the pin and another
player’s ball, and how to yell “fore!” to warn other players when one of our shots went astray.
We learned the last skill very well. Golf strengthened our connections with Dad and
Granddad. We heard their stories about learning golf, celebrated (or more often &lt;em&gt;lamented&lt;/em&gt;) the
current state of the Oklahoma State football program, and shared nuggets of wisdom and humor
as we walked the course together in the blazing Oklahoma sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/golf.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Golf&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Photo taken at the first hole (I know because my hopeful grin is still present)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hamburgers-ice-cream-and-slideshows&quot;&gt;Hamburgers, ice cream, and slideshows&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, the highlight of every summer undoubtedly was the celebration of Independence Day and the
coinciding visits by aunts, uncles, and cousins. Our house often became the hub for these family
reunions, and Mom and Dad were gracious hosts. Mom always prepared her famous baked beans
and potato salad to go along with the best hamburgers west of the Mississippi. Dad had the honor
of grilling the burgers, perhaps with a little bit of help from his sons, and cranking (for what
seemed like hours) the homemade ice cream freezer. The food was fantastic, and laughter always
filled the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the last bowls of ice cream were being consumed, Dad prepared the slide projector for the grand
finale - a photographic recap of our family’s past year including birthdays, holidays, and
vacations. In the days of sharing photos on Instagram and Facebook, I now miss the quaint
click-click of the slide projector and the accompanying “oohs”, “ahs” and laughter as we
celebrated another year with family. Dad’s warm smiles indicated that he knew the importance of
family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;star-gazing-and-star-trek&quot;&gt;Star-gazing and Star Trek&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summer days often concluded with star-gazing and Star Trek!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dad, Mark, and I shared a love of astronomy and space exploration. As youths, we could not read
enough books about the stars and planets and often tuned-in to NASA television news conferences
in which scientists discussed the latest findings and spectacular images from space probes such as
Voyager (exploring Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, and Neptune) and Viking (landing on Mars).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dad encouraged our love of astronomy by buying us a small telescope which allowed us to view with
our own eyes what we had seen in photos and on television. Seeing the rings of Saturn and the moons
of Jupiter through our small telescope sparked my imagination and cemented my decision to pursue
science or engineering as a career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will never forget how Dad made a way for us to see Halley’s Comet in 1986. Early one morning
before sunrise he drove us several miles east of town armed with binoculars and star maps hoping to
get a glimpse of the famous visitor to the night sky. Although the comet was fuzzy and faint,
two boys and one father shared an amazing and unforgettable experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our love of astronomy and space exploration extended into fiction as well, and I can remember
spending many late nights as a teenager with Dad and Mark watching the original Star Trek re-runs
on television. Although these shows may seem “campy” to viewers today, we recognized the strong
stories and relevant messages that apply outside of the realm of science fiction. As I recall,
these late-night viewings led to some of the first deep discussions with Dad about many of the
problems and injustices that impact our world. Dad’s values continue to shape my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May each of you have a wonderful Father’s Day!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mike Sturm</name></author><category term="Astronomy" /><category term="Golf" /><category term="Gardening" /><category term="Family" /><category term="Sports" /><category term="Summer" /><category term="Dad" /><summary type="html">For my brother Mark and me, this is our first Father’s Day without Dad, who passed away in March. For many years, Alzheimer’s Disease slowly robbed our family of Dad’s full presence. At first, it slightly diminished his exceptional intellect, giving the rest of us a fighting chance to win an occasional round of Liverpool Rummy. As it progressed, this horrible illness stole his words and deprived him of the ability to recount humorous stories from his childhood and verbal expressions of his love for us. Ultimately it claimed his life, long before it should have ended.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raspberry Pi Aquarium Monitor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/pi-aquarium-monitor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raspberry Pi Aquarium Monitor" /><published>2020-05-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/pi-aquarium-monitor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/pi-aquarium-monitor/">&lt;p&gt;Before we get started, I can anticipate many of your questions about this blog post already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Why do you have a typo in your blog title?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“What does a delicious fruit dessert have to do with aquariums?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have a computer geek in your life, you may not realize that a &lt;strong&gt;raspberry pie&lt;/strong&gt; is
quite different from a &lt;strong&gt;Raspberry Pi&lt;/strong&gt;. The latter is a low-cost, single-board computer
created by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/about/&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, a non-profit
organization based in the UK that brings the power of computing to students and hobbyists
around the world. The “Pi” in the title not only suggests the pi symbol from mathematics but also
the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; computer programming language. &lt;em&gt;Hint: I am a fan of both!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fell in love with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi&lt;/a&gt; for projects because it
reminded me of the early days of personal computing when my brother and I spent countless hours
tinkering around and learning how to program using our
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_II_Plus&quot;&gt;Bell &amp;amp; Howell Apple II+&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-fish-tancing&quot;&gt;Social “Fish-tancing…”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around Christmas, my son Jacob, who is studying journalism at Oklahoma State University in
Stillwater, purchased a 20-gallon aquarium and stocked it with several freshwater fish.
Establishing a new aquarium can be a painful process, and he lost several fish during the first
few weeks until the beneficial bacteria started breaking down the waste. By the beginning
of March, the aquarium had reached a “stable” state – right in time for his planned trip back home
to visit us during Spring Break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is when the world changed. What started out as a week-long visit to Edmond turned into weeks of
quarantine due to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coronavirus_disease_2019&quot;&gt;COVID-19 pandemic&lt;/a&gt;.
Bringing the aquarium to our house was out of the question, as the move would likely disrupt the
careful balance he worked so hard to establish. Traveling back and forth to Stillwater to care for
the fish was possible but impractical. This dilemma required a creative solution to allow him to
keep an eye on his tank while he was home with us in lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cue-the-raspberry-pi&quot;&gt;Cue the Raspberry Pi…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Raspberry Pi is one of those devices that you &lt;strong&gt;know&lt;/strong&gt; you want, but you may not have a
concrete &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; to buy. Sure, its purchase can be justified for educational and entertainment
uses, but can it do &lt;strong&gt;useful&lt;/strong&gt; things? Yes! Faced with the aquarium dilemma, I quickly knew how
my Raspberry Pi Zero W would be put to use for the next several weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pizerow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Raspberry Pi Zero W&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Raspberry Pi Zero W&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the aquarium monitor project, I used off-the-shelf components that are available for purchase
through &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adafruit.com/&quot;&gt;AdaFruit&lt;/a&gt;, or other
Raspberry Pi vendors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/products/raspberry-pi-zero-w/&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi Zero W&lt;/a&gt;
single-board computer is the centerpiece of the aquarium monitor. Although it sells by
itself for only $10, it requires some additional components such as a power supply
and micro SD card to store the operating system. For my project, I used the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Vilros-Raspberry-Starter-Power-Premium/dp/B0748MPQT4/&quot;&gt;Viros Raspberry Pi Zero W Kit&lt;/a&gt;
($29) along with a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B012PLSCQ0&quot;&gt;Lexar 633x 32GB micro SD card&lt;/a&gt; ($6).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recording images and videos of the fish requires a camera module, and for this project, I used the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/products/camera-module-v2/&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi Camera Module v2&lt;/a&gt;,
which sells for $28 on
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Raspberry-Pi-Camera-Module-Megapixel/dp/B01ER2SKFS&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;.
The camera is connected via a ribbon cable to the Pi Zero W and fits nicely in the Vilros camera
case included in the kit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We purchased an inexpensive, timer-based &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B07VCKRFGY/&quot;&gt;fish feeder&lt;/a&gt;
which automatically dispenses flaked fish food twice per day at 10 a.m. and 6 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The aquarium light is connected to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wemo.com/&quot;&gt;WeMo&lt;/a&gt; smart plug, and it is
programmed to turn on at 10 a.m. and off at 8 p.m. daily.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Pi is mounted to one of my spare tripods so that the entire aquarium is visible in the
camera’s field of view.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;software-runs-the-show&quot;&gt;Software runs the show…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Pi Zero W runs an optimized version of the free and open-source
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux&quot;&gt;Linux&lt;/a&gt; operating system called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/downloads/raspbian/&quot;&gt;Raspbian&lt;/a&gt;. Raspbian is similar to Windows and
macOS in that it can run programs and handles interfacing with the computer hardware.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/raspbian-desktop.png&quot; alt=&quot;Raspbian Desktop&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Raspbian Desktop&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I needed to be able to access the Raspberry Pi from our house over the internet to make
adjustments to the camera settings and video schedule from our house. To do this, I used the
Real VNC server (included with Raspbian) running on the remote Raspberry Pi and the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.realvnc.com/en/connect/download/viewer/&quot;&gt;Real VNC Viewer&lt;/a&gt; on our home computer
to remotely control the Raspberry Pi over the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wrote a simple &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bash_(Unix_shell)&quot;&gt;bash&lt;/a&gt; shell script which
invokes the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;raspivid&lt;/code&gt; program to capture a couple of minutes of video and send it to another Pi
at our house using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/SSH_File_Transfer_Protocol&quot;&gt;SFTP&lt;/a&gt; protocol.
The bash script is invoked every hour, on the hour, between 10 a.m. and 7 p.m. when the aquarium
light is on.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our home Raspberry Pi receives the video each hour and, after the 7 p.m. video arrives, another
bash script on that device combines all of the daily videos into one video which is ready to watch
at our leisure.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;putting-it-all-together&quot;&gt;Putting it all together…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few iterations of tweaking the bash scripts and adjusting the positioning of the camera,
we were very pleased with the end result. We can check-in on the daily activities of the
fish to make sure they are healthy, the water level is correct, and the food is being dispensed
properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/IS_rwr9qUGo&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to watch a recent video of the aquarium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pi-aquarium-monitor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Raspberry Pi Aquarium Monitor&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Raspberry Pi Aquarium Monitor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pi-camera.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Raspberry Pi Camera&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Close up of the Pi Camera&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;geeky-details&quot;&gt;Geeky Details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have read this far and want more details, this section is for you. Otherwise, feel free
to stop reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bash-script-on-the-remote-raspberry-pi&quot;&gt;Bash script on the remote Raspberry Pi&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the following bash script for the video recording on the remote Raspberry Pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;aquarium-&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sb&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt; +%b-%d-%H-%M&lt;span class=&quot;sb&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;
raspivid &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-o&lt;/span&gt; ~/Aquarium/&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$filename&lt;/span&gt;.h264 &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-t&lt;/span&gt; 120000 &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-drc&lt;/span&gt; med &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-ISO&lt;/span&gt; 160 &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-fps&lt;/span&gt; 20 &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-a&lt;/span&gt; 1036

sftp pi@my-home-pi.my-dynamic-dns-provider.com&amp;lt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;EOF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sh&quot;&gt;
lcd ~/Aquarium/
cd /mnt/samba/Backups/Aquarium/
#put &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$filename&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sh&quot;&gt;.mp4
put &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$filename&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sh&quot;&gt;.h264
quit
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;EOF

&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;rm&lt;/span&gt; ~/Aquarium/&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$filename&lt;/span&gt;.h264

&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;SFTP_RETURN_CODE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# If the return code is non-zero then the upload was not successful&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt; 0 &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;SFTP_RETURN_CODE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;then
   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;upload failed&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;SFTP_RETURN_CODE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else
   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;upload successful&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;fi

&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;exit &lt;/span&gt;0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;raspivid -o ~/Aquarium/$filename.h264 -t 120000 -drc med -ISO 160 -fps 20 -a 1036&lt;/code&gt; command
invokes the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;raspivid&lt;/code&gt; program for 120000 milliseconds (2 minutes) and saves the output the
specified file name. I am using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-fps 20&lt;/code&gt; to limit the frames per second to 20 (which I found was
acceptable and reduced the file size). The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-ISO 160&lt;/code&gt; was another tweak to prevent parts of the
video from being overexposed. Finally, the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-a 1036&lt;/code&gt; is a way to add the time and date on the video.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sftp&lt;/code&gt; command shown does not have my &lt;strong&gt;actual&lt;/strong&gt; IP address. I have added the SSH public
key for the remote Raspberry Pi to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/.ssh/authorized_keys&lt;/code&gt; file on the home Raspberry Pi.
That way the remote Pi can send the files without sending the password (since the SSH keys are
used for authentication).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bash-script-on-the-home-raspberry-pi&quot;&gt;Bash script on the home Raspberry Pi&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The home Raspberry Pi is responsible for combining all of the recorded videos from the day into
a single video which makes it easier to review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; /mnt/samba/Backups/Aquarium
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;aquarium-&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sb&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt; +%b-%d&lt;span class=&quot;sb&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;
MP4Box &lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for &lt;/span&gt;file &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in &lt;/span&gt;aquarium&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;h264&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;do &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-cat&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$filename&lt;/span&gt;.mp4
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;rm&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;.h264
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MP4Box&lt;/code&gt; program is used to combine all files from the day (which are named starting with
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aquarium&lt;/code&gt; and with the extension &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.h264&lt;/code&gt;) into a new file in MP4 format.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After processing the files, remove the hourly &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.h264&lt;/code&gt; videos.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cron-jobs&quot;&gt;cron jobs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bash scripts are invoked through &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cron&lt;/code&gt; jobs which are created using the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;crontab -e&lt;/code&gt; command
and using an editor to add scripts which will be invoked at certain times. The important lines
are shown here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# m h  dom mon dow   command&lt;/span&gt;
0 10 &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; /home/pi/Scripts/camera.sh
0 11 &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; /home/pi/Scripts/camera-3min.sh
0 12 &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; /home/pi/Scripts/camera.sh
0 13 &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; /home/pi/Scripts/camera.sh
0 14 &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; /home/pi/Scripts/camera.sh
0 15 &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; /home/pi/Scripts/camera.sh
0 16 &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; /home/pi/Scripts/camera.sh
0 17 &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; /home/pi/Scripts/camera.sh
0 18 &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; /home/pi/Scripts/camera-3min.sh
0 19 &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; /home/pi/Scripts/camera.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;crontab settings for remote Raspberry Pi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The time is specified using minutes (first number), hour (second number), day of the month, month
number, and day of the week. An asterisk &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; is used to indicate ‘any’.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the example above, the script &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;camera.sh&lt;/code&gt; is executed at 10 a.m., 12 p.m., 1 p.m., 2 p.m.,
3 p.m., 4 p.m., 5 p.m., and 7 p.m., while the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;camera-3min.sh&lt;/code&gt; is invoked at 11 a.m. and 6 p.m.
(which happens to be our feeding times).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Mike Sturm</name></author><category term="Raspberry Pi" /><category term="Linux" /><category term="Family" /><summary type="html">Before we get started, I can anticipate many of your questions about this blog post already.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nobody eclipses my Mom!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/mothers-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nobody eclipses my Mom!" /><published>2020-05-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/mothers-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/mothers-day/">&lt;p&gt;Happy Mother’s Day! I apologize for the cheesy pun in this blog post title, but bear with me
as I recall a very special trip spent with my wonderful Mom and two of my children. And…
of course this statement is true!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a certified astronomy geek and &lt;del&gt;slightly&lt;/del&gt; very obsessive family trip planner, I could not
wait to drive hundreds of miles to witness
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solar_eclipse_of_August_21,_2017&quot;&gt;The Great American Eclipse of 2017&lt;/a&gt;.
I considered this to be a &lt;em&gt;once-in-a-lifetime&lt;/em&gt; opportunity to see a total solar eclipse, even though
I knew there will be another &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;(even better)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; total solar eclipse in April 2024,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solar_eclipse_of_April_8,_2024&quot;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Greater&lt;/em&gt; American Eclipse of 2024&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was disappointed that my Dad (who was in a nursing home), as well as my wife Cindy and eldest son
Jacob (both of whom were in class), could not join us on the trip, but I was thrilled that I
would get to share this exciting time with my Mom, my daughter Katie, and my youngest son, Luke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oklahoma-city-to-potosi-missouri&quot;&gt;Oklahoma City to Potosi, Missouri&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our trip began on the afternoon of Sunday, August 20, 2017, as Katie, Luke, Mom and I drove for hours
to a small town southwest of St. Louis for our hotel in Salem, Missouri.  This town was not in the
path of totality but within about 1.5 hours of a town called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Potosi,_Missouri&quot;&gt;Potosi, Missouri&lt;/a&gt;, which was off the beaten
path of eclipse-watchers but close enough to the center of the totality path to provide about
2 minutes and 13 seconds of totality.  Originally I planned to make the much shorter drive
to near Kansas City, but at the last minute I changed our hotel because the weather prediction
called for clouds and possibly rain during the eclipse.  I am so glad we were able to find a
hotel near the path of totality. We were treated to a great view of the eclipse in a nice city
park in this small town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/eclipse-watchers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Waiting for the eclipse&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;partial-eclipse&quot;&gt;Partial Eclipse&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading up to the totality was like other partial solar eclipses I have witnessed.  The
partly cloudy sky and surrounding park were slightly dimmed at first, and we got a reprieve from
some of the hot weather as more and more of the sun was covered by the moon.  We all enjoyed
taking a peek from time to time during the early eclipse, wearing our glasses carefully of
course.  Otherwise, we hung out in the shade or in the running car with A/C on this hot day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/eclipse-sunspots.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Partial eclipse, sunspots&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within a few minutes of the totality, the dimness increased to the point of being very odd.
I showed everyone the crecent shaped shadows on the ground, as the light shining through the
leaves (and our fingers) emulated “pinhole cameras”.  Then the rapidity of the approaching
darkness was striking as the totality began.  The sky above was not pitch black, but rather
like 20-30 minutes after sunset.  On the horizon it looked like a strange sunset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;totality&quot;&gt;Totality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the first few seconds of totality, I was messing with my camera and laptop.
Beforehand, I had programmed a sequence of shots into the computer, which triggered my
camera’s shutter using different exposure settings which I found on the internet.  The
settings were designed to capture different parts of the totality.  It worked perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I finally got the computer sequence started, I looked up and was blown away by how
beautiful and surreal the view was.  I’m struggling to describe it in words, but it almost
seemed like the moon was a very large, black marble in the sky blocking out the sun.  It
looked slightly three-dimensional to me.  Around it we could see the brightness of the sun’s
outer atmosphere - the corona.  The shape of the corona is affected by the sun’s magnetic
field, and in the photos you can see interesting line patterns caused by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/totality-aug21-2017.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Totality&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of my planning included an app on my phone which prompted us about the totality based
on our GPS location.  That was very handy because it warns you when to put the glasses back
on.  After just two minutes and 13 seconds, we were warned to wear our glasses and, sadly,
the totality was over.  The surroundings brightened very rapidly, and it was starting to
look more normal again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the eclipse ended quickly, our thoughts of this shared adventure lingered
for much longer. It was such a moving and emotional experience, unlike any other. I recall
that the beauty of totality moved my Mom and me to tears. We shared an amazing moment which
I will never forget. I continue to cherish my memories of this time with my Mom and
children, chasing &lt;strong&gt;The Great American Eclipse&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nobody eclipses my Mom!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mike Sturm</name></author><category term="Astronomy" /><category term="Eclipse" /><category term="Family" /><category term="Mom" /><summary type="html">Happy Mother’s Day! I apologize for the cheesy pun in this blog post title, but bear with me as I recall a very special trip spent with my wonderful Mom and two of my children. And… of course this statement is true!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Tribute to My Dad</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/tribute-to-dad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tribute to My Dad" /><published>2020-03-02T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-03-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/tribute-to-dad</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/tribute-to-dad/">&lt;p&gt;My Dad, Gene Paul Sturm, Jr., of Bartlesville, OK passed away on March 2, 2020 after years of
struggle against Alzheimer’s Disease. Below is a tribute to my father, friend, and mentor.
I will never forget him and his tremendous, positive impact on my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the book of Matthew, Jesus teaches&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Love the Lord your God with all your heart and with all your soul and with all your mind.
This is the first and greatest commandment. And the second is like it: Love your neighbor as
yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Matthew 22:37-39 (NRSV)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that my dad understood and believed these words by the way he lived his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dad demonstrated his &lt;strong&gt;love for God&lt;/strong&gt; not only through sharing his faith and values within our
family, but by recognizing the image of God in everyone and by marveling at the beauty of the
universe He created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dad demonstrated his &lt;strong&gt;love for his neighbors&lt;/strong&gt; by selflessly serving his community, his friends,
and especially his family.  He practiced sacrificial love, putting his own needs below the needs
of those he loved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/genesturm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gene Paul Sturm, Jr.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; recipient of Dad’s love, and his values forever shaped me into the husband and
the father I am today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who always believed the best in people instead of the worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who valued honesty and justice for those in society who were overlooked
and marginalized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who was brilliant but never made you feel any less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who taught that loving God and loving science are not mutually exclusive
but the truest expressions of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who believed in me as I pursued my educational and career dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who showed me how to treat family and friends with unrelenting love and
respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who loved my wife like his own daughter and who had overflowing love and
pride for his grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am mostly &lt;em&gt;thankful&lt;/em&gt; for a dad who taught me to &lt;strong&gt;love God and love others&lt;/strong&gt; - the values I
need to live my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will miss Dad until I see him in Heaven, but I know that I carry his values with me every day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mike Sturm</name></author><category term="Family" /><category term="Dad" /><category term="God" /><category term="Christianity" /><summary type="html">My Dad, Gene Paul Sturm, Jr., of Bartlesville, OK passed away on March 2, 2020 after years of struggle against Alzheimer’s Disease. Below is a tribute to my father, friend, and mentor. I will never forget him and his tremendous, positive impact on my life.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Christmas Presence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/christmas-presense/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christmas Presence" /><published>2010-12-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2010-12-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/christmas-presense</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/christmas-presense/">&lt;p&gt;One of my fondest childhood memories of Christmas has to be &lt;em&gt;The Cheetah&lt;/em&gt;.  No, I am not talking
about the fastest of all land mammals.  For those of you who were not a young boy in the early
1970’s, the cheetah was the pinnacle of ride-on toys.  This was no wimpy “Big Wheel” - its name
promised a more exhilarating experience.  I imagined that with this vehicle, I could zoom down
my neighborhood sidewalks in Bartlesville, Oklahoma as fast as the animal for which it was named.
In my mind it epitomized the ultimate Christmas gift, and of course I let everyone know it was
at the top of my wish list.  The memory of receiving this gift and racing down the street is
clearly imprinted in my memory to this day.  Few other gifts made this kind of impression on me
growing up.  Of course there were a few exceptions, but for the most part I do not remember
many of the other Christmas presents from my childhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/cheetah.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Cheetah&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;traditions&quot;&gt;Traditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say my memories of Christmas are fuzzy.  Christmas was always a time of great
anticipation at our house, and not only for the toys that were sure to be opened on the night
of Christmas Eve.  For us the season started around Thanksgiving with our annual trek up into
the attic to retrieve the boxes of decorations.  Climbing into the dusty attic seemed like a
rite of passage to me, and if you saw my wide eyes you would think I was on a safari or other
adventure (perhaps to a galaxy far, far away).  Usually this ritual found my dad crawling back
to the far corners of the space and pushing box after box to me.  I would either take the boxes
down the stairs or hand them to my brother below.  We felt so proud to help with the boxes.
Because of our family tendency for horrible allergies, our Christmas tree came in a box with
each branch color-coded to indicate the placement on the green metal “trunk”.  Even though
artificial trees can never fully substitute for the beauty of a real one, our tree always
seemed beautiful to us despite being loaded down with so many ornaments, lights, garland,
and icicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Christmas Eve, the celebration kicked into high gear.  I always looked forward to the special
candlelight church service, not so much for the many Christmas carols we sang but for the
opportunity to hold a lighted candle in church!  Cool!  At the front of the sanctuary advent
candles were lighted, and the flame was transferred one by one to individual handheld candles
throughout the room.  My family usually sat in a pew towards the back of the auditorium, so to me
it always seemed to take forever to get the flame to our candles.  I swear that on some nights
“Silent Night” was almost over by the time the flame arrived.  As I remember, the experience of
holding the candle and raising it up and down at key moments of the song was well worth the wait.
It is a miracle that our church didn’t burn to the ground given the number of children wielding
fire!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/fcc-sanctuary.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First Christian Church, Bartlesville, OK&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course after “Silent Night” concluded, all that was on my mind was getting back home to the
Christmas presents.  No chatting with other families - let’s go home!  Presents awaited us at the
house, not to be outdone by dozens of snacks prepared by my mom.  There were pretzels covered in
chocolate, peanut butter balls dipped in chocolate, chocolate pie, and did I mention chocolate?
A deli tray with cuts of meat and cheese awaited those who did not crave sweets.  Usually my
brother and I were able to convince the family that we should open the presents before (or at
least during) snacking.  The eager boys would always hand out the presents, and then all of us
would go around the room opening our gifts in order of youngest to oldest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the hoopla surrounding Christmas Eve subsided, Christmas morning was somewhat anticlimactic.
It was time for one “Santa” gift plus some token gifts in the stockings.  At the risk of sounding
like an old-timer, the only apple products in our stockings were the edible kind…. and we
LOVED IT!  (Okay, this comment was for the benefit of my children who are usually treated to iPods,
DVDs, and CDs.)  I also remember sometimes getting to meet Santa at our house.  One of my family
members would dress the part and deliver mesh “stockings” filled with fruit and trinkets.  I don’t
remember if we knew it was him in the Santa suit or not - I guess we were too mesmerized by the
fruit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/santa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Santa Claus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;christmas-presence&quot;&gt;Christmas Presence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now as a husband and father of three, I look back at my childhood from a different perspective.
Just as countless other parents have discovered through the centuries, I appreciate Christmas as a
time for families to connect and reconnect.  As the charity Advent Conspiracy so cleverly reminds
us, Christmas is about presence not presents.  Christmas presence is being there (and not
twittering on your iPhone) with your spouse and children.  Christmas presence is creating family
memories and meaningful traditions.  Christmas presence is sharing God’s love with others through
sacrificial generosity.  Most of all, Christmas presence is reflecting on how much we are loved by God.
God gave us His presence in the form of a baby born in Bethlehem about 2000 years ago.  With the birth
of Jesus, God told the world that he wanted an intimate relationship with each one of us.  He wanted
to be present in our lives just like a good father is for his children.  God modeled perfect love for
us not from afar, but with us, in person on this planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so thankful for my parents, brother, grandparents, aunts, uncles and cousins for sharing
Christmas experiences and loving me in my childhood.  I am so thankful to have a wonderful wife and
children (and extended family) with which to create new Christmas memories.  Most of all, I am
thankful to Jesus for sharing His Christmas presence with the world.  I guess for me Christmas
presence is all about thanksgiving.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mike Sturm</name></author><category term="Christmas" /><category term="God" /><category term="Christianity" /><summary type="html">One of my fondest childhood memories of Christmas has to be The Cheetah. No, I am not talking about the fastest of all land mammals. For those of you who were not a young boy in the early 1970’s, the cheetah was the pinnacle of ride-on toys. This was no wimpy “Big Wheel” - its name promised a more exhilarating experience. I imagined that with this vehicle, I could zoom down my neighborhood sidewalks in Bartlesville, Oklahoma as fast as the animal for which it was named. In my mind it epitomized the ultimate Christmas gift, and of course I let everyone know it was at the top of my wish list. The memory of receiving this gift and racing down the street is clearly imprinted in my memory to this day. Few other gifts made this kind of impression on me growing up. Of course there were a few exceptions, but for the most part I do not remember many of the other Christmas presents from my childhood.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Parable of the Comet</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/parable-of-the-comet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parable of the Comet" /><published>2010-11-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-11-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/parable-of-the-comet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/parable-of-the-comet/">&lt;p&gt;I have a confession - I am an astronomy geek.  That may not be much of a surprise to those of you
who have seen my 8 inch telescope or watched my excitement looking to the skies from a dark,
country location away from the bright lights of the city.  Astronomy captured my imagination early
in my life and has captivated me ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;for-the-love-of-comets&quot;&gt;For the love of comets…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of my astronomical affection is focused on the lonely comet.  Astronomers theorize that many
of these small bodies of dust and ice orbit our sun at a very great distance in a large spherical
Oort cloud.  Small tugs of gravity from planets or other stars may cause one of the cold, dark
comets to plunge towards the sun into the inner solar system where it may put on a spectacular
show.  Comet tails of gas, dust, ice are blown away from the comet by the solar wind and
illuminated by reflected sunlight.  Given a favorable combination of proximity to Earth and angle
of illumination by the Sun, a comet’s tail may appear to stretch across a considerable portion
of the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the most famous of all comets is Halley’s Comet.  The orbit of Halley’s comet causes it
to visit the inner solar system about once every 75 years, and for the 1986 visit I was eager to
catch a glimpse of my first comet.  In spite of cautions from astronomers that this particular
appearance of the noteworthy visitor would be disappointing due to the Earth’s position relative
to its approach, my family and I set off one cold spring morning to view the comet before sunrise.
With star maps in hand we were barely able to find the fuzzball near the southern horizon.
Spectacular comets would have to wait for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, that day came ten years after the dismal performance of Halley.  In March 1996, Comet
Hyakutake passed very close to the Earth, and because of its close proximity and long gas tail,
this comet was simply incredible to behold from the pitch black sky I found near Stillwater,
Oklahoma.  I was amazed by the huge tail that seemed to span about half of the sky like a giant
search light.  Armed with a 35 mm camera, tripod, and fast film, I captured some of my first
photographs of a comet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/hyakutake5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Comet Hyakutake, near Stillwater, OK 1996&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a year later, another incredible comet graced the Oklahoma skies.  Comet Hale-Bopp, predicted
to be bright and beautiful, did not disappoint those who saw it over several months of naked-eye
visibility.  I captured a photograph if it hanging above the silos at my wife’s family farm near
Cushing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Hale-Bopp-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Comet Hale-Bopp, near Cushing, OK 1997&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On November 4, 2010 the NASA EPOXI spacecraft will fly by Comet Hartley 2, and of course I will
be following the encounter on the NASA website!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;parable-of-the-comet&quot;&gt;Parable of the Comet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder what it must have been like for our ancestors to see comets hanging in the sky.  For
those without electric lights to artificially brighten the sky at night, comets would have been
more visible, impressive, and perhaps even ominous.  History records that ancient peoples often
feared comets as foreboding signs of horrible events to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Bible does not record any stories that Jesus told about comets, I imagine that he
would have pointed to comets not as signs of evil but rather demonstrations of God’s love for us
and reminders of our relationship with the Son.  For you see, we are all like comets created from
dust left over from an ancient supernova.  When we are far from the Son, our hearts are frozen and
we are alone in darkness.  Yet even in our darkest moments, the Son draws us to Him.  As we humbly
approach the Son, our hearts melt and we lose ourselves in the warmth of His love.  The Holy
Spirit is a wind from the Son that strips away our hurts, loneliness, and selfishness and reveals
the Son.  The nearer we get to the Son, the more we reflect His light to others who are watching
in the darkness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love comets because they draw me to the Son.  When I look up at the amazing universe that God
has created, I want to live my life reflecting the Son’s light - not to draw attention to myself,
but to lead those in the darkness to Him.  After all, God loved each of us so much that He gave
us the Son, and whoever approaches the Son will not be filled with coldness, darkness, and death
but with warmth, light, and life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mike Sturm</name></author><category term="Astronomy" /><category term="Comet" /><category term="God" /><category term="Christianity" /><summary type="html">I have a confession - I am an astronomy geek. That may not be much of a surprise to those of you who have seen my 8 inch telescope or watched my excitement looking to the skies from a dark, country location away from the bright lights of the city. Astronomy captured my imagination early in my life and has captivated me ever since.</summary></entry></feed>